when it occurs in nature all
intelligence is collective
intelligence any any real physical
intelligence system that you can think
of is composed of you know a bunch of
subordinate intelligences that are in
turn you know and I mean you know
depending on how far you want to take
the whole it from bit wheeler thing it
goes all the way down to like Quantum
fields and atoms and all of that stuff a
nice place to start might just be if you
tell me a bit about that your work
versus AI um because it's kind of using
to my understanding active inference and
theories and cognition to kind of help
us think about and create AI so that
might be a cool place to First maybe
introduce active inference and and then
think about how that relates to things
like Ai and then we'll see where it goes
absolutely that's a great place to start
um so yeah I'm Maxwell ramstead I'm the
senior director of research at versus AI
uh versus is a cognitive computing
company um and uh basically we're in the
business of uh taking the explanatory
principles that have been you know
discovered in neuroscience and the
sciences that study cognition broadly um
and turning them into design principles
uh for artificial artificial
intelligence systems um in particular
we're interested in the physics of
information U this has also been called
basian mechanics so the physics of
probabalistic
beliefs um and applying that to build AI
systems that are genuinely able to take
a perspective on the world um and you
know engage in active inference right so
uh active inference being kind of online
real time uh perceptual inference and
action
selection um so yeah uh my uh my
background is uh multidisciplinary like
you were saying mainly philosophy and
computational Neuroscience uh I work
closely with Carl friston um who uh is
the originator of uh active inference
and free energy principle and all those
nice things um so yeah we we've been
around for um going on half a decade
pretty soon at
versus um and yeah we have a we have a
very active inferenced focused lab
actually we'll be we're coming out of uh
our cocoon this year um and we'll be
rolling out some Benchmark work
comparing active inference based AI to
more
standard uh you know it's sort of it's a
weird historical circumstance that we
now think of like deep learning as just
kind of state-of-the-art standard
vanilla stuff but yeah we we'll be
benchmarking um and hopefully showing
you know a
genuine advantages to flipping yeah it
would be interesting if you could tell
me a bit about the the challenges and
even the thought process of like
thinking about why you could apply
active inference and these theories of
understanding cognition to AI because
yeah as you say we've been creating like
things like large language models and
these more like generic and these you
know interesting models in their own
right um but they're not things that in
in many ways are sort of directly
analogous to how our own cognition works
so how's it has it been trying to think
about AI in this life
well I mean you can think of active
inference as like going full
Bay U so it's a fully basian approach
where U we're basically using um one
objective function the variational free
energy to optimize um the full kind of
stack of intelligence right so um we
variational free energy it sounds
sometimes like a little bit esoteric
it's a quantity from information Theory
and essentially it quantifies the uh the
Divergence or the distance between the
data that you expected under some model
of how the data are produced um and the
data that you actually get so the
interest one of the interesting things
about using variational free energy is
the kind of
backbone um for your stack as opposed to
say reward is that you can do the whole
inference uh you can do you can do
inference on several different time
scales which essentially covers all the
different like forms of intelligence
that you might uh encounter in uh in
real time so there's perceptual
inference or state
estimation right which is basically uh I
think I have a hypothesis I think the
world is in a certain configuration or
State uh if the world was in that
configuration or state then I would
expect to get a certain pattern of data
um and then I can use the Divergence
between the pattern that I got and the
pattern that I expected to refine my
hypotheses right and you end up
selecting the hypothesis that has the
lowest free energy which means like that
the that that generates data that's the
most consistent with the data that I'm
actually getting but you can take that
up a level right if you have like one
layer of inference running at like kind
of state estimation level um then you
can do uh you can do inference about the
the parameters of the uh actual model
like the structure of the process that's
generating um your your data so you can
uh learn things like the transition
probabilities and the likelihood uh that
Maps your uh basically the states
causing data to the data um that is
caused by those
States and so yeah you you you get this
nice kind of parameter learning again
it's the exact same uh it's the exact
same objective function you're just
iterating it at a slower time scale uh
so in some sense it's kind of making
inferences about your own inferences and
then at the top layer you can actually
do whole wholesale and model selection
using the same right so uh there it's
not the value of parameters but the
actual like existence of parameters
within the model the way that they're
hooked up to everything um so yeah it
gives you a nice principled kind of
bottomup approach to building a whole AI
stack based on the same core techniques
everywhere which I think is uh pretty
cool um historically
the the reason these methods haven't
been deployed at scale is that basian
techniques are are sometimes difficult
to scale I mean there are a number of
problems with scaling for example where
do your priors come from um and um what
one of the things that we've been
doing at versus is uh breaking the
basian wall socalled um so figuring out
efficient techniques uh that allow you
to yeah deploy approximate basian
inference it's scale without running
into you know the usual intractability
problems that you run into with base you
know the problem with basian reasoning
is that at the end of the day you need
to renormalize everything uh it's
probability distributions right so your
posterior is proportional to your
likelihood times your prior but it you
need to
normalize in order to get probability
distributions like that that uh
integrate to one and so on back from
from that and often the the uh the this
denominator that you need to like
normalize with is
intractable um so yeah we've developed a
bunch of alternative techniques uh
they've existed in the literature
variational Bays is a way of getting
around this so you replace uh an
intractable exact inference problem with
a tractable optimization problem um and
that's gotten us
uh a big a big part of the way to our
objective so yeah you you'll be hearing
a lot about these results over the
coming year um but it's been a it's been
very exciting um to develop all this
stuff yeah it's helpful I mean one one
thing I want to say is that when you
talk about having to think about active
inferences occurring at many scales
right so kind of a benefit of like
applying that to AI is that in a way
obviously that that is how the brain and
how how active inference is occurring
within us right it's kind of easy to
like say if you're reading a paper
hearing about active inflence like oh
yeah you know we predict and then we
receive you know sensory data back and
we update that but that's occurring you
know at the you know say top level of
the cortex but then like lower levels of
the brain I mean even like individual
cells must be kind of maybe having their
own it's it's going you know from from
the lowest levels up to the highest
levels in like in these iterative
processes um and and I suppose like any
AI kind of might need to have that I
guess think about normal like attention
models and things that they're also like
let's try and get more Nuance here by
like predicting not just one one level
but like you know how how how accurate
uh like intermediary stages going to be
so so yeah very you're putting your
finger on something very critical here
which is the and I think this is from a
from a global or general kind of design
perspective this is where we are most
uh uh I wouldn't say like in conflict
with but like we're most opposed to the
kind of standard foundation model
approach um so it when it occurs in
nature all intelligence is collective
intelligence any any real physical
intelligence system that you can think
of is composed of you know a bunch of
subordinate intelligences that are in
turn you know and I mean you know
depending on how far far you want to
take the whole it from bit wheeler thing
it goes all the way down to like Quantum
fields and atoms and all of that stuff
um so yeah uh the way that nature has
solved the problem of you know
intelligent behavior is to offload
intelligent Behavior to communities of
intelligent that are able to at The
Ensemble level solve problem so even you
know you as an individual are you know
the you emerge as an entity from the
coordinated interactions of uh you know
an unthinkable number of different
agents that are competent in their own
domain yeah you know like uh as my my my
liver does its thing right and my you
know your pancreas does its thing and
your heart and then the all of these
specific kind of intelligences that are
uh expert within their domain right my
my heart does the blood pumping and my
pancreas does the etc etc uh something
more emerges from that and so that's
that's the blueprint that we're using um
ADV veres uh and I think more generally
uh within the active inference approach
to really understand intelligence so
like we're not trying to build uh the
monolith ADV veres right we we kind of
think that there's a problem currently
with uh the idea of kind of building a
machine God just like is one monolithic
centralized system that just like
encodes all of like that that's just not
it's not that's not how nature designs
intelligence is and there are reasons to
think that this is not like an efficient
way to go um you know the there's a what
we need um for the future AI of AI is to
go I think in opposite direction right
like what ideally and you know our our
kind of end goal and we outlined this in
our white paper which was recently
published uh so the the paper is called
designing ecosystems of intelligence
from first principles and that's
precisely what we're trying to do right
we're trying to design ecosystems of
intelligent agents some of which are
quote unquote artificial uh and some of
which are quote unquote natural like us
um but yeah the uh
so I think if you think of
AGI artificial and general intelligence
is often presented as the north star of
AI research and this can mean a bunch of
different things usually in the more
plausible sense what people mean by AGI
is something like a system that's able
to perform at human level uh on a bunch
of tasks um which you know I guess is
fine as far as it goes like that's
aable uh and reasonable engineering
objective right um but the the concept
of AGI is kind of incoherent when you
stop and think about it for a few
minutes in particular intelligence is
not General there's no such thing as
general intelligence like all
intelligence is tailored to specific
kind of situation and reflects you know
contextually appropriate adequate
Behavior within that context right um
even things that might seem General like
mathematical reasoning and logic are
still Fair narrow applied forms of
intelligence like there's no such thing
as general intelligence so you know
there's a sense in which uh the I think
a lot of the industry is kind of chasing
a myth
here um there is there's no such thing
as general intelligence so forget
artificial general
intelligence that's probably not what we
want to be aiming at uh especially if we
want to have realistic and achievable
objectives
would you say so it's interesting
because obviously us as human agents we
do have the ability to have you could
say deploy intelligence across many
different domains but would you think
you think it's just better to
conceptualize that is not a kind of
intelligence or like as something I mean
you can think about it as a kind of
intelligence but what I mean is like so
you know you're uh your pancreas right
is an expert at secreting different
kinds of things that that's a of
intelligence right like these are like
living organ systems that are constantly
monitoring your internal State your
internal
mear um and uh you know secreting
appropriate things when appropriate
that's a form of intelligence like I I I
I I as an organism like as as an agent
I'm not very good at secreting
B right like this is what I mean like uh
you know uh certainly abstract you know
reasoning and stuff is applicable in a
bunch of different domains but when
you're thinking about like
intelligence there there are various
kinds of intelligence that are just not
equivalent to I think like abstract
logical reasoning if that makes sense uh
even this kind of you know the IQ or
whatever gets captured under the G
factor or whatever I mean it's not it's
not completely General uh in that sense
right like it uh it's a it's a specific
kind of expertise that is Deployable in
specific kinds of domains like any other
you know
competence um yeah and I think it's a
bit misleading to think of that as like
general intelligence when it's just it's
just another it's a highly specialized
form of symbol mainly symbolic kind of
reasoning right like this isn't it's not
as
general as all that really given that
you well well that's interesting because
in in in reformulating intelligence in
this way this this white paper you guys
wrote on sort of ecologies of different
agents and intelligences how does that
that fit in so you know when you're
building you know AI that are based more
on the kinds of active inference that we
as human agents might do and and perhaps
I'm just you you can tell me are they
maybe more interpretable and unless you
know we can kind of uh see in what ways
they relate to us I'm just I'm just
wondering how should we to check
okay um
so okay active inference-based AI
architectures um are constructed to be
human interpretable or transparent
that's a big difference right uh so in
our stack we don't use any black
boxes uh we use uh you know it's a
similar kind of model architecture right
but
um every parameter every node that we
deploy is explicitly labeled and
corresponds to some aspect of the
underlying situation trying to model um
so you know our approach to you know
deploying AI in a given situation would
not be to like you know create this
monolith that in theory has information
about every context whatsoever it's to
deploy agents that are expert within a
specific you know situation or domain of
expertise right um and uh then you know
to create an ecosystem of such agents uh
that are able to you know deploy in in
real time uh you know they're these are
lightweight agents so to speak right
like you're not talking about agents
with like 10 trillion parameters I mean
just taking one step back I guess the
fundamental difference is what you mean
by
infms right there's a there's a sense in
which um llms and the current deep
learning networks are engaging an
inference uh I mean essentially what
you're doing when you're querying one of
these models is creating a conditional
probability uh distribution right so
like you have you have your model and
then you're saying well I have I have
this data so conditioned on this data
the models output is in some sense like
a big conditioning process and there's a
sense in which well because this kind of
process conforms to the rules of you
know basian probability or whatever you
can think of it as a form of inference
all that is good um you know and I
wouldn't want to say that these systems
don't engage in inference because they
do in that sense like the computations
that they perform uh you know respect
the laws of probability Theory B and all
that therefore it's um but in the active
inference liter literature when we talk
about inference what we have in mind is
changing your mind in light of new
information in real time right uh which
is marketly different um so on our
definition systems like you know chat
GPT were engaged in inference uh during
their training and then their Deb on
arrival right because that's that's the
that's the point at which they're in
contact with the the world generating
data right so you train these things it
takes three months it cost you $100
million 70% of which is like you know
electricity bills and then it's Dead on
Arrival like that to us that's not like
genuine
intelligence uh I mean it's a kind of
glorified database or lookup table which
again you know I don't want to knock uh
these Technologies you know deep
learning is a huge Advance uh and you
know just like 10 15 years ago like this
was like the absolute pioneering
bleeding edge of what was going on and
I'm sure these Technologies uh you know
have a future to a certain extent um but
you know it's
just what you need if your aim is to do
things like you know drone control and
realtime robotics like what you need is
to be able to have a system that has a
perspective on the world and is able to
change that perspective update its
beliefs in real time based on the
information that it's generating
continuously right that's really the end
goal in some sense um you're not going
to get that uh with systems that like I
said take months to train then to train
here means to do one passive inference
where you're updating your whole model
based on your data set right um yeah so
we're trying to in summary uh draw upon
you know the billions of natural
R&D the the you know the universe
consists in in some sense right natural
experiment
um to design more efficient uh AI
systems you know there's a lot of talk
about how the uh next AI Revolution
might need something like uh you know
new new power sources or something we
need to develop nuclear fusion or
whatever to be able to I mean it doesn't
seem like many people have considered
that hey maybe these you know the the
brain runs on a banana and a glass of
water right like I don't need a nuclear
fusion power plant running my brain like
it runs on 20 watts right so yeah if if
you need like you know if you literally
need to build new power plant you're
probably doing something wrong right
like and so uh but there is another
approach and it is to learn from nature
and do things uh
parsimoniously uh another way to think
about what we're doing is that we're
moving from Big Data to I I hesitate to
say smart data I guess Frugal data might
be more appropriate
um one of the things that we'll be uh
demonstrating actually is the vastly
improved sample efficiency of our system
uh so we don't need big data um to to
train our systems uh because we deploy
systems that are intelligent about how
they use
data so you you seek out informative
stimuli and you update your beliefs
right and that's really the key like in
some sense we uh it's sort of like the
scientific method extended to AI itself
it's like we're building little systems
that have a hypothesis about the way the
world is and then just need to like be
perturbed a little bit and test the
hypothesis against incoming data and
that's really the loop you know I have I
have some idea some belief about how the
world is and then uh necessarily because
the map must be simpler than the
territory I'm going to encounter some
you know there's going to be like some
uh resistance there's going to be some
Divergence right and then you update
your your map and when I say like this
is a feature like the the map is
necessary necess I'm saying this is a
feature the map is necessarily simpler
than the territory right so you know you
say you're you're based in the UK how
useless would a onetoone scale map of
London
be like imagine trying to look something
like just imagine the paper that would
you would need right like so the map has
to be simpler than the territory to be
useful um and so if you have a
simplified map of the territory then
what you can do is use the Divergence as
the
signal to to then you know make
decisions decide what's going on and to
yeah plan and Route yourself through
London right I I like the so there's so
many interesting things there but like
on that point of pointing to the sort of
immense efficiency of of humans uh the
fact that they kind of you know quick
inference right so it's almost there's
there's information out there already in
our natural environment and it's just
the ability to extract sort of the right
information at the right time um I was
talking to um a researcher uh from
Michael Lev's
Laban yeah and he and he we were talking
about uh like you know on your point of
um maybe we'll run out of literally the
ability to produce electricity and like
transistors because you know the models
we need to make it just so enormous um
then that is like the the bottleneck and
that makes me think that the more the
more AI progresses the more it has to be
almost in that podcast that I just
mentioned we we talked about we have to
make computation and and AI more like
humans and we need to like try and learn
from like how cells actually fire how
neurons fire um because again like how
can we unlock that efficiency and like
that natural ability to be parimon
and so it's like AI kind of more and
more must sort of look a bit like us to
to to have um the kind of capacities
that we might want them to have yeah
absolutely there's no sense Reinventing
the wheel right like we want to build
intelligent machines well you know every
time a baby is
born an intelligent machine has been
created in fact uh so you know why not
just borrow from nature right like that
it seems like a very par
way to approach this um and it's
probably the only sustainable way to do
it frankly um like you know whenever uh
you know some new technological
Revolution the slogan is we're going to
need new energy sources to power this
yeah it's probably not like it's
probably not a path path sustainable
development right like so I couldn't
agree more yeah on this point of um
sustainability of producing AI I'm
wondering what you think of so I was
thinking about how in like how say um
large language language models are
trained like a lot of it is by the
internet but I was thinking in a way the
internet is kind of just like one
enormous database but we only have one
of it the thing is is a thing and so if
you train on that you can train on the
whole thing as much as you can that is
actually useful but once you've done
that it's like what more is there to
kind of do you've kind of like you you
know there are ways you can like get
humans to interact with it and train it
but that's that's that's that's slow and
it's you know it's not again it's as you
say you know these large langu models
are doing inference but you know like
they're doing again and again but then
you once you actually have them um then
they're no longer doing that that
inference uh so so the the training kind
of is all before but you know we think
about us you know we can learn kind of
instantaneously and then try new
Behavior yeah um I mean I I I agree with
all that um not sure what to add I think
well I'm glad yeah I'm glad you say that
that like CU um you know one thing I was
listening to um you may not know him but
but Jonathan P was was talking about uh
you know uh once these large language
models start like producing their own
new content and things like now the
internet will be filled with more of
what they have produced so it's a kind
of regurgitation like we got the
internet but it's only one data source
now you start producing more but it's
like where does you know new real live
information about the world come from
with them so exactly so what what what's
going to you know the the future of AI
is IA right the future of artificial
intelligence is intelligent agents right
and that that's that's ultimately you
know where I think the you know the
relevant data is going to come from it's
going to come from the real the real
world right like ultimately the you know
the the internet is sort of like history
right like you know it's it's it's a
repository of all of our knowledge and
everything but uh you know what what we
would want is to create systems that are
able to assess situations in real time
and act within them in a way that
conforms to you know our highest ethical
standards our you know the general
regulation that conforms to like laws
and customs and the you know uh so to
create agents that have some sense of
what is contextually appropriate and
then who act in contextually apprpriate
ways in real time based on the data that
they generate through their actions in
effect so I I agree the that sort of
speaks to like the this idea of the
spatial web that we're developing so the
versus has a nonprofit sister
organization called the spatial web
Foundation um and part of what we have
done um as a kind of Tandem is to um is
to create a stand standardized World
modeling
language we are we are gifting to the
itle e um if everything goes well it
should be uh publicly available this
year um so it's called hyperspace
modeling language um and it is I mean
you know this is part of the general
push towards an ecosystem intelligences
right like so um what would you need to
create like a kind of Patchwork of you
know specialized agents well one thing
that you would need is a kind of
standardized set of tools to design
agents in a way that you might you know
have a repository for example of
different agent types that are already
appropriate to act in a given kind of
setting right so the this kind of um you
know the the metaverse you might think
like of as you know the virtual reality
and other but there's this notion
especially in the east of the physical
metaverse which is more like a blurring
of the lines between physical reality
and the digital world uh where in some
sense like our kind of representation of
reality in a world model becomes part of
the control Loop itself right so u i
mean it's very ambitious sounding and
everything but the the the hope is to
kind of move towards like doing for
infrastructure um and just technology
generally what nervous systems do for
organisms and their bodies right kind of
create this kind of backbone of
coordination uh allowing you know uh
specialized systems to be deployed in
specialized circumstances in an
appropriate way um you know the brain
works like this right like so um I
really like Michael Anderson's work he's
got a a great book beyond phenology
where he proposes uh that essentially
the the way the brain works um is that
that uh the brain brain areas are
computationally specialized not
functionally specialized I mean there's
very interesting he does some meta
analyses it draws on very uh recent uh
you know neuroimaging work and
everything to show that well you know um
even areas that we think of as
functionally specialized aren't really
so so one of the things he points out
for example is the brokas area that
famous area that's supposedly
responsible for the production of speech
it's involved in more non-speech tasks s
than in speech related tasks so what
that tells you is each bit of the brain
is actually specialized to take like a
configuration in and to spit out a
modified configuration so they're
computationally specialized modules and
what the brain is doing in real time on
Anderson's account which I think is very
compelling account is to assemble
transient ensembles transient neural
assemblies that basically on the Fly
pick out which contributions need to be
brought to bear to solve the problem in
in real time right so you know like
you're you're listening to someone
you're going to recruit like the parts
of the brain that you need to shuffle
that pattern into the the appropriate
kind of pattern and then produce the
appropriate response so we're basically
trying to do to AI what you know brains
do in some sense to in the kind of
compositional modular structure uh and
kind of just take this strategy but
right at large right to say well you
know there are certain agent types that
you might depl like drone agents camera
agents car agents whatever uh and then
you know you can like kind of tune them
as specifically as you want to the
specific context in which they're going
to be uh needed and deployed ultimately
so you can think of this kind of build a
brain If you I yeah yeah I really like
you bringing that in that that that
brain are is a well that they kind of
it's more specialized in in um ways of
of doing computation um because it kind
of It kind of again points to we talking
at the start about everything being a
kind of collective intelligence and the
more like I was listening to Michael
Evan recently talking about um like even
if you're using like you know very
simple like you know agents of like
literally like small code blocks the
more and more agents you have up to a
point there's a there's like a critical
point where the more and more you have
like they almost each of them uh can
give their own like you know ideas their
own perspective and so it's like if you
just have enough things you know they
can search almost such space almost so
you know you know human intelligence is
a lot like this U sperber and Mercier
are two cognitive anthropologists that I
like a lot um and they put out a book
called the Enigma of Reason which you
may have heard of uh and their whole uh
argument I mean they make a bunch of
very interesting contributions in that
book but one of the interesting things
that they point out is that we think of
confirmation bias as a kind of mistake
right like it's a kind of mistaken
heuristic but um provided that we have
instruments and tools to exchange
reasons amongst ourselves right
confirmation bias is is the optimal
search strategy it's it's much easier
especially if the brain operates like
active inference suggests right where
you have a belief and then there's a
Divergence and you know what you're
trying to do is to in some sense change
your mind as little as possible given
the new
information receiving trying to be uh
parimon about the way that your
information the information that you're
getting is changing your beliefs well
it's most efficient if everyone H is
very kind of strong minded about their
beliefs and looks for evidence to the
effect they're right so long as others
can say hey actually you're wrong about
this and consider this evidence so they
they they propose like my side bias as a
better way of understanding the
phenomenon of confirmation bias which is
see I'm going to be biased towards my
own beliefs but provided that we are a
community and that we have like you know
the appropriate communication protocols
and channels then that actually turns
out to be an optimal search strategy and
yeah you can think of like collective
intelligence more broadly as that you
know uh the immune system is another
great example of that where you have
like these cells that uh are essentially
are kind of like a register for you know
okay we'll produce this kind of antigen
and this kind of context and everything
um and uh yeah it's all about like you
know activating the right cells and
getting those populations to effectively
clone themselves in order to like
generate an appropriate immune response
so you know uh what in some sense what
we're trying to do is to build this out
like move move from like explanatory
principles to like genuine design
principles for artificially intelligent
system interesting I was going to even
bring up the Enigma of reason you know
that the fact that we actually should be
biased in our reasoning if because if
individually we all are then
collectively we're more likely to get to
to the right result um and even
relatedly I was reading a paper on
bacteria and how it seems that like
looking at like the species of bacteria
is actually kind of irrelevant so again
doesn't matter like what it is just like
in a brain reion region we actually you
shouldn't split up as like where you
know it's more actually like they almost
fill functional roles um the different
it doesn't matter what species they are
and actually in some days useful to
think about you could say the kind of
computations the kind of thing they're
doing in that Collective and as long as
like everyone FS certain things then
overall like the way I was understanding
is that even bacteria they have kind of
niches and so like they almost work like
a little ecosystem and they can all help
each other survive and it's just someone
someone needs to fill one role and
someone needs to fill the other that's
correct yeah I mean on the active
inference view what you have at the end
of the day is like this nesting of agent
environment
relationships um so like at in some
sense my body is an environment for the
organ systems that make me up right and
in turn each of these organ systems is
an environment for you know the
individual organs that compose it and
and so on and so on right or organs are
an environment to the relevant cell
types and cells are an environment of
the relevant organel and nuclei and all
this stuff and so on and so forth all
the way down like you can really think
of like the uh you can think of
biological self-organization as a kind
of stack of environment organism
relationships like you know so echoing
like ecological psychology and this kind
of stuff but maybe uh maybe stretching
some of the concepts to the breaking
point like I had disagreements with
ecosy people uh it seems like they want
you know affordances to pick out one
specific layer of the stock which is
like the
organismal that of the organism I kind
of feel like it might be more fruitful
to just blow that up and to think of the
affordances that are available to cells
the affordances that are available to
organ systems and so on so you really
have like this genuinely multiscale
ecological kind of approach that opens
up with active inference that I find
quite
exciting yeah oh fascinating um so so
we've talked about Collective
intelligences um Ai and and the future
so maybe another uh you know easy and
simple topic would be uh Consciousness
just you know easy just you know another
another another um classic topic uh no I
mean yeah it's and and I guess the
reason why I want to bring that up now
especially is because you know we talked
a lot about things needing to be agents
um or or not that's that's kind of an
open thing you know just the way it
seems is that you know maybe like again
you you had a paper on active inference
kind of needs to be named inactive
inference it's so much of it is about
asess you say sampling the world and
doing things and and so yeah know maybe
maybe one way to start is yeah how
should we think of Consciousness in
light of active inference and the free
energy principle and and maybe even what
it says about Ai and that's a great set
of questions so I think um it was uh
debated amongst us in the FP literature
whether the FP really had anything
unique to say about
Consciousness um I guess like at one end
of the of the question
um we've proposed and when I say we it's
folks like folks like anel Seth and
myself uh and our co-authors uh you know
ton luds and a few others we we proposed
a few years ago this project of
computational
phenomenolog um so this is a kind of
um it it's it's deploying the free
energy principle and active inference um
as a modeling meth methodology for a new
kind of data which is phenomenological
data so like okay just roughly speaking
um the context of Discovery for you know
active inference the free energy
principle and so on um is a generative
modeling in neurophysiology so a
generative model is a model of process
that generates the data that we're
interested so originally these
techniques were first developed in the
context of neurophysiology ology
neuroimaging where the data that we're
interested in is uh indirect or direct
measurements of brain activity usually
indirect so if you're talking about
fmri uh so functional magnetic resonance
imaging Works basically by uh detecting
the magnetically active byproducts of
oxygen use by neurons so the neurons use
oxygen when they they burn you know ATP
and all that stuff and about five to six
seconds after that activity there's a
temporal lag but with very high spatial
Precision you're able to say okay oxygen
was used here because you got this so
the the signal that you pick up is
called the Bold signal blood oxygenation
level
dependen and then so what you what you
use generative models for in that
framework is to say okay well what is
the most probable set of underlying
neurophysiological responses that would
have elicited that bold signal and in
that context well you have a bunch of
different models that that represent
what the underlying phys physiological
activity might be and you use free
energy minimization right you say well
the the model that's the most probable
is the model with the least free energy
so I have you know the data that I
picked up and then a bunch of models
saying well if if this was the activity
then you would get that data and you end
up picking up the right picking the
right model by picking the one with the
lowest free
IMG um active inference is the same idea
but now the data that I'm trying to
explain isn't data that I'm generating
using a big magnet thing it's the data
that my eyes my ears my skin all of my
sensory organs are uh generating and
then the model isn't a model of the
underlying neurophysiological activity
that that you know caused the data that
I'm picking up it's a model of me acting
in the
environment right but it's the same idea
right like I think I'm acting in this or
that way I think I'm walking in a
straight line U on a street and then
there's a Divergence and then I realize
that oh you know like I slipped and I
fell or whatever right like so it's but
it's the same idea like you have a
generative model a model of the process
of generating my data it's just the data
type is change so uh generative modeling
is agnostic to the data type that you're
interested in computational
phenomenology is the idea that we can
basically generate descriptions of
first-person experience using
phenomenological or other qualitative
first person methods and then write down
a generative model of that
phenomenology so kind of um you know
then there's a kind of two-step process
where once you've written down a model
of that phenomenology well that
constrains the space of possible models
that might ex you know uh be related to
the brain processes underlying
that um so that's one whole project uh
it doesn't say anything about whether
Consciousness it's self conforms to the
free energy principle it's just saying
well um you know and maybe taking one
step back for the purposes of the
audience because we've been talking
about the free energy principle uh
Without Really defining it so the free
energy principle is a principle of
information physics and it basically
says if I exist in the physical Universe
in the sense that I can be reliably
reidentified as the same thing over time
by an external Observer then it'll look
as if that thing is tracking the thing
things that it's
coupl another way of thinking about it
is that the Fe is a is a principle of
information physics applied to coupled
random dynamical systems and it says
that random dynamical systems that are
coupled will appear to track each other
by virtue of the fact that they're
coupled but
separable right so sort of like um you
know if you were talking about one thing
then it would all kind of blur and
diffuse you know like cream in a coffee
right um but since there talking about
two separate things the best you can do
is that they begin to resemble each
other you don't get like one kind of
like you know uh light brown colored
coffee you get like two kind of things
that couple to each other um so yeah and
so the free energy principle says if you
exist in the physical Universe then
you're going to look as if you infer
what you're coupled to and clearly uh
you know in some sense
um systems that are conscious are things
and therefore they they should be
modelable using the free energy
principle so then you're not making any
strong kind of commitments about what
kind of thing Consciousness is and the
free energy principle isn't necessarily
Illuminating like the the Deep nature of
Consciousness when you're doing this
it's really like okay this is a general
modeling framework and can apply to
anything clearly my experience is such a
thing and therefore we am I am I right
go on no no go go well just want to say
am I right so then in saying that yeah
the free eny principle like it's one
framework to apply to something like
cognition but like inherently doesn't
say anything like something has to be
cognition or whatever it's like it's
about like yeah objects in the world and
so it's it's about things it's you can
think about it as a a mathematical
approach to
thingness per se so you know and it's
been mischaracterized by by myself in
the past for example as a theory of
organisms and living is um it it it can
be used as the basis for such a theory
but intrinsically it's even broader than
that um it's it's a theory of thingness
if you're a thing in the physical
Universe in the sense that you don't
just dissolve into your environment then
you necessarily will conform to this
principle like it's going to look as if
you're tracking what you're
coupl okay um so the key construct
behind the free energy principle is this
idea of a marov blanket which you may
have heard of um and so yeah the marov
blanket is essentially the interface
between something and what it is
not um yeah so I mean in some sense you
can think of the marov blanket as all of
the degrees of freedom that couple two
systems together and that separate those
systems so the the set of degrees of
freedom that separate and couple two
systems um so we were talking about
computational phenomenology given the
marov blanket I can talk about the
opposite extreme view which I think can
coexist but it's it depends on what your
interest is like if you want to say
something about Consciousness per se or
if you want to just you know model
interesting kinds of experience in a
kind of like you know neuro
phenomenology style um so the marov
blanket in some sense is where all of
the information that describes the
coupling between two systems
lives right so if two things are coupled
everything that you need to describe
that coupling by definition lives on the
blanket it's where all of the classical
information that describes the coupling
lives so um the uh the hypothesis that
was put forward a few years ago by Chris
Fields uh Jim glazbrook and Mike Levan
um in a a grade paper I think it's
called minimal physicalism or something
like that uh they proposed the inner
screen hypothesis which is to say say
that well um if if classical information
must live on the blanket then maybe
Consciousness is related to the
existence of an inner
blank or uh in other words Consciousness
requires internal
boundaries right um so we have this
we've elaborated this in a whole paper
which is uh you know pre-printed and
currently under revision um yeah the uh
the idea there is that Consciousness
corresponds to uh the existence of this
kind of irreducible internal screen
where the system that you're considering
is kind of partitioned in such a way
that like some of the information that's
relevant to its actions lives on a kind
of inner
screen and um yeah you can kind of see
this as a a naturalization of the
pulus maybe provocatively so I we've
been going around calling this like neoc
cartisian
um yeah uh we we do avoid the kind of
infinite regress because the idea there
is that the inner screen does not
observe itself the most it can do is
observe subordinate
screens uh so you know what when when
you think about like the cortical
hierarchy we usually focus on each layer
and say well this layer is connected to
this layer is connected to this layer
the the perspective from the free energy
principle says don't focus on the layers
focus on their interface the the same
structure is actually just a series of
screens between the layers and what the
screens do in effect is coar grain the
subordinate screen right so like you
know you have at the sensory end you
have you know screens that kind of
encode all of the information coming up
welling up from the sensory ends and
then as you ascend the cortical
hierarchy what each successive screen is
doing is basically core screening so
kind of removing the ex access kind of
information and saying well all of these
things are basically this and you know
there there is at the top and at the
bottom two screens that are right only
in some sense right the sensory end can
only push things in and at the very top
it can only write down right um and
that's really the key we think to like
the reflexive aspect of
self-consciousness like there exists an
irreducible layer that in some sense can
only in infer itself into existence it
doesn't have direct access to itself it
has to infer that it exists through its
effect on the other layers and
ultimately the bottom layer being the
sensory motor interface itself uh its
effects on the world so yeah so there is
something a bit more robust that you can
say about Consciousness based on the
free energy principle it's very
speculative right now like you know
we're we're in the very very early days
of modeling this but we'll be uh moving
moving into a more kind of experimental
setting and actually like testing out
these
hypotheses uh over the next few years
interesting um to see if I understand it
I mean that this inner kind of is it so
is it basically people kind of before
they would be like kids obviously there
is a boundary by which things interact
that's that's the point of the freey
principle but no one sort of thought
about wait what it's going sort of on
more inside of that thing doing that
that interaction um and uh and yeah it's
the way it does sound a little cartisian
but it's like not necessarily or like it
has to be something looking at a screen
but more is it to be honest like you
know deckart is one of the most like
misunderstood philosophers like ever uh
honestly I don't think I don't think you
know depending on the time in history
that you're considering deckart is
everyone's
favorite like person to use as a foil
right so uh in the 18th century de art
was uh criticized for inventing
physicalism and the soulless Clockwork
Universe right uh more more recently
like in the 20th century dickart uh gets
beaten up because he's the inventor of
dualism and brings like the mysterious
soul back into where you know so
depending on the period you know deart
is accused of a bunch of stuff when he's
actually like struggling with some
pretty uh core questions and you know
you have folks like Merlo ponti who
everyone loves but who took deard very
seriously you may know this Merlo ponti
died from a stroke reading while he was
reading
Leon didn't know yeah it died on his
desk like reading deart which
is it's it's it's it's you know I mean
but it's interesting I think jnan V has
also talked about like we kind of
misunderstand dear and he had like loads
of great things and I I think we should
think about that a lot well I should
because it's easy to be like you know
you hear other people criticizing
philosophers and obviously we want make
progress and it's necessary to think
about ways in which some might be wrong
but like you also have to appreciate
like how amazing a thinker they would be
um that's why we're talking about them
and maybe think I don't think philosophy
makes progress that's not how philosophy
work um so it's
like it's it's in this theory of of
Consciousness then um uh I've kind of
heard you talk a little bit about it
before like ultimately sometimes I
wonder like it and and I'm guilty of
this too we kind of maybe sensationalize
Consciousness like we don't even want to
think it's something that can be
understood because it's it's so
interesting how could it just be reduced
to to things so there's like a there's
like also a part of you which goes like
I will there's no Theory Of
Consciousness I'd ever accept you know
and that can be that can be problematic
so but but yeah is is it an answerable
question to think about like though
though even like you know things have
their own inner inner like like you know
um Mark of blanket as well and this
could be
fundamental to Consciousness but I'm
interested in like uh why do we feel
like we have a unified Consciousness
then Andes that is there way of going
about explaining that and I experience I
think that's precisely what the inner
screen model large part explains right
because the the basically the when if
you're considering each layer of the
brain is like course graining the
following there you reach a layer where
no more Co graining is possible so there
is an a topmost layer
and you know it it this doesn't have to
be like a pyramid right it maybe that
like 80% of the brain subserves that
kind of top
layer um but yeah I mean um I I would
think that this kind of the the the
structure of the flow of information
throughout the brain kind of imposes
this kind of
centrifugal sorry centripetal kind of
but um on the flip side though I think
uh one of the great lessons um of you
know say
psychoanalysis and the uh the
phenomenology that is closer to
psychoanalysis so like I'm thinking of
recur and people like that I think it
was Merlo ponti who said you can
recapture all of the core Freudian
insights by abandoning the intuition
Consciousness is at all times
unified and you know when I think about
my own Consciousness like I'm a little
bit ADHD brain and U like I I don't feel
like my consciousness is Unified into
one flow all the time certainly may
that's my own pathology but uh yeah I
think it's a kind of it's a very um it's
probably not the most fruitful way to
think about Consciousness is like
continuously
unified um I mean the the self might be
something like that but then I would
recommend looking at the work of St Anil
Seth um to kind of get some insight into
why the the self might be a stable thing
although I think given the given the
time that we have remaining that's
probably too big a yeah I even Point
people to John vei and and some of his
colleagues had a series called The
elusive eye which is like even if yeah
even if you know even like K young
talked about like there's an an ego
which is a bit Elusive and only one part
of of a bigger self but there is a way
in which like through narratives through
over time through our connections with
others there is there are these things
which B
all the different parts together and um
un like a final thing is that um you
talk about sometimes you don't feel like
you're necessarily unified and and you
know Frey def like you know would say
there are different parts of us and
there's some great work by people like
Damien kely Stevens talking about like
um the the multifractality of think
sometimes things bind together and there
are like there are these flow these flow
like nature to to our movements where
like we we suddenly have these like uh
critical moments of coordination and
everything comes together but but there
are also like at all times you could say
like small brain processes small small
movements like going in other directions
and and that's how and we can sometimes
stop them but then sometimes we let them
happen and so there is a a kind of flow
in nature where um we are letting as
we've been talking about you could say
smaller subsystems smaller computational
levels that are allowed to do their own
thing see different possibilities see
different and even you know embodied
more active possibilities and and and
then there are sometimes with
FR Francisco Vela in his work no I don't
think I don't think so verela has this
uh this great little collection on
ethics um actually uh where he talks
about like micro
selves so like the self is basically
like a pasti of micro selves that are
like appropriate to certain context um
yeah and again I think we overemphasize
the degree to which we're like
integrated and uh you know unified that
might be like a kind of Hangover from
Enlightenment
philosophy um you know like a kind of
it's basically a through Line running
from deart to Hegel effectively this
kind of unified self idea um I think uh
you know the the Freudian Revolution
slash you know the cognitive Revolution
kind of undermine that premise really
significantly um you know it's a and
which brings us back I think
appropriately to the beginning right
like intelligence is collective
intelligence uh and you know I think
even even if our our sense of self is is
Unified and one that doesn't mean that
that unification and Oneness doesn't
emerge from a kind of you know Patchwork
or meshwork of you know different selves
interacting um so all of these things
can be true we can have our cake and eat
it too
with thank you um this has been great so
where can people find your work and do
you have anything more you want to say
um well uh you can follow our
developments at versus. a um I'm um I'm
quite active on X Twitter um which is
where I think we met um so yeah that's I
I basically post everything there um and
yeah we will'll be regularly posting our
updates um like I said on versus uh. I
there's a whole R&D subsection I'd
recommend following our blog we uh
regular well more increasingly regularly
uh we'll be putting out um yeah short
pieces uh kind of explaining to an
informed play audience what we're doing
um and you'll yeah that that's probably
the easiest way to keep track of what
we're doing um let me just Express
gratitude uh for the invitation this has
been a really fun conv ation and yeah um
hope you have a great one yeah I Le
those too so thank you
[Music]
awesome